<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sabbato-dominica. Or, A few propositions tending to reoncile [sic] the seeming difference, between the lettter [sic] of the law and Christian libertie, in the doctrine of the Sabbath and the Lords day, briefly propounded, explained, and confirmed. Together with an Appendix, unto the same propositions, tending to satisfie some exceptions likely to be taken to them. By Irenæus Philalethes. Or, one, that unfainedly desires to keep the unitie of the Spirit in the bond of peace, and speaking the truth in love, to grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even Christ.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B29226</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832303</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207311</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248538707</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S212</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832303</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99832303e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B29226)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207311)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2057:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sabbato-dominica. Or, A few propositions tending to reoncile [sic] the seeming difference, between the lettter [sic] of the law and Christian libertie, in the doctrine of the Sabbath and the Lords day, briefly propounded, explained, and confirmed. Together with an Appendix, unto the same propositions, tending to satisfie some exceptions likely to be taken to them. By Irenæus Philalethes. Or, one, that unfainedly desires to keep the unitie of the Spirit in the bond of peace, and speaking the truth in love, to grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even Christ.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 123, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.P. and M.S. for Phil. Stephens, at the golden Lyon in Pauls Church yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207311:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207311:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sabbato-Dominica.</hi> OR, A FEW PROPOSITIONS tending to reoncile the seeming Difference, between the lettter of the Law and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Libertie, in the Doctrine of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> and <hi>Lords day,</hi> briefly propounded, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, and confirmed.</p>
            <p>Together with an <hi>Appendix,</hi> unto the same <hi>Propositions,</hi> tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to satisfie some exceptions likely to be taken to them.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Irenaeus Philalethes. OR,</hi> One, that unfainedly desires to keep the unitie of the Spirit in the bond of peace, and speaking the truth in love, to grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even Christ.</p>
            <q>Many shal run to and fro, and knowledge shall be increased. <bibl>
                  <hi>Dan. 12.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T.P.</hi> and <hi>M.S.</hi> for <hi>Phil. Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phens,</hi> at the golden Lyon in Pauls Church yard. 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:207311:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207311:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE HOVSE OF <hi>COMMONS</hi> now assembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen publick report, the great Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of the world, had filled almost all mens minds with an earnest expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that by the advise and order of this Honourable House a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Synod would be shortly assembled, or at least a choise
<pb facs="tcp:207311:3"/>number of the best Divines se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to assist the high Court of Parliament, in ordering the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of Religion in this Land; some (who had seen these little Treatises, and thought there might some good use be made of them, as ayming, in a moderate way, at the discovery of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Truth, which all men ought to seek, and that in some particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of importance, which have of late been much disputed) did not onely, as formerly they had done, move me to permit the publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, but likewise to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, by way of Preface, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with relation to the expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Synod or Assembly Which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse that course were setled al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready,
<pb facs="tcp:207311:3"/>I know not how to do bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then by craving leave of this Honourable House (as the great hinge upon which that heavenly motion hangs) to cast these little Treatises, as the poore widow did her two mites, into the treasurie of the Temple: and humbly to professe, that my intent is not, in any thing wherein I vary from others, to engage either them or my self in the maintenance of our own opinions, but with willing submission unto better judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, onely to offer occasion of consideration unto all, in some particulars, which otherwise per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps might lye belowe their thoughts. Truth drops not alwaies from the clouds, but sometimes
<pb facs="tcp:207311:4"/>springs out of the earth, and at a little spark of fire on the hearth (if it be not with too strong a breath blown out at the first) a candle may be lighted for the use and benefit of all that are in the house. That I conceal my name is rather out of conscience of mine own unworthinesse, and a desire I have to avoid the very shew of affectation, then fear to fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the censures of any. For pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate imputations, I shall let them passe, as going but on equall ground: but if publick Authoritie, either in the voice of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable House, or otherwise, shal stoop so lowe, as to interpret it a fault, I shall willingly submit my self to censure, thankfully receive,
<pb facs="tcp:207311:4"/>and patiently undergo deserved punishment, and still continue to pray, as I do, that the Spirit of wisedome and understanding, the Spirit of counsell and might, the Spirit of knowledge and of the fear of the Lord may rest, and be so multiplied upon you all, that the issue of all your consultations may be such, as may give all men iust occasion to ioyn in consort with the Angel and the heavenly host in praising God and saying, <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unto God in the highest, and on earth peace, good will towards men: that our eyes may see the King in his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Ierusalem a quiet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, a Tabernacle that shall not be taken down, nor
<pb facs="tcp:207311:5"/>any of the stakes thereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, neither any of the cords thereof broken.</hi> Which he that hath so long ago promised wil certainly at length in his good time perform, if men have but faith enough to wait with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that after they have done the will of God, they may receive the promises, which in Jesus Christ are, yea, and Amen, unto the glory of God, who is the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and onely Potentate, the King of kings, and Lord of lords, to whom he honour and power ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:207311:5"/>
            <head>TO ALL THAT SEEK THE TRVTH so, as becomes the Friends of Peace and Holinesse.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the <hi>Sabbath</hi> be a day of rest, yet the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions, that have been moved about it, I doubt not, will be restlesse, untill that truth be brought to light, wherewith, if not all, yet moderate minded men at least, may rest themselves satisfied. Some of that truth I think I have found, and that appertaining to the very foundation, upon which the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<pb facs="tcp:207311:6"/>observation of the Christian <hi>Sabbath</hi> or <hi>Lords day</hi> is grounded, <hi>viz. the perpetuall morality of the fourth Commandment.</hi> Which whilest some have openly set them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of purpose, with all their might and maine, not onely to deface, but also to demolish utterly, crying, <hi>Down with it, down with it, even to the ground:</hi> they have been much encouraged, on the one side, by those, who, thinking to settle it surer, have onely cemented with sand, or daubed it over with untempered morter; by the weaknesse of their evidence brought the strength of their cause more in question, and made it seeme lesse defensible to them, that had a mind to bend their force against it, when they saw the defendants so poorely provided, disdaining them as <hi>Goliah</hi> did <hi>David,</hi> and triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the victory, as if they would have said, <hi>Videas ante de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectet contra retiarium ferula:</hi> on
<pb facs="tcp:207311:6"/>the other side by those, who presuming it capable of such superstructions, have raised a vast pile of rigorous impositions upon it, enough almost to crush it to pieces. So that the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Sabbath</hi> or <hi>Lords day</hi> began to be crucified between Superstition and Profanenesse, as Christ himself, the Lord of the Sabbath, was between two theeves: and they, that had a mind to try their strength, in resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it unto its ancient right, found their passage unto their adversaries such, as <hi>Jonathan</hi> and his Armour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer had to the garison of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listines, between <hi>Bozez</hi> and <hi>Zenah,</hi> a sharp rock on the one side, and a sharp rock on the other side, which to climbe up they had need to make use both of their hands and feet. This consideration, together with the solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citations of some private friends, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout five yeers ago, set me on work, to search about this foundation, to see if I could find upon what ground it
<pb facs="tcp:207311:7"/>stood, and whether their mouthes, that were disposed to cry down the morality of the fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with so much confidence, as if there had been no colour either of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or of reason for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance thereof, might not be stopped, and the edge of those arguments aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whereby they made account, they should cut asunder all the sinews of that opinion for ever: whether the head of that Philistine, which defied the armies of the living God, might not be cut off with his own sword, and the reproach taken away from Israel.</p>
            <p>That endeavour then brought forth these Propositions, wherein though the principall thing, that I aymed at, was to enquire, whether the morality of the fourth <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> might not be made manifest, by such evidence, as nature it self might see sufficient reason to subscribe unto, yet I thought by the way I had met with such truths, as might serve to
<pb facs="tcp:207311:7"/>give some ground of satisfaction un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other doubts, both in the doctrinall and practicall part, which I drew in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to corollaries or conclusions, such as I thought might be naturally dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, from the same Propositions. But knowing how apt men are to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ween their own works, and resolving that I might be though willingly I would not be deceived, I did both of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten enter into examination of that which I had done my self, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, as opportunitie was offered, submit it unto the censure of others. Which course occasioned, though no alteration in the maine, yet some ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions unto that which I had done at first, and at last brought forth that Appendix, wherein I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to remove all the doubts, that probably I could conjecture might be made of any thing therein. And now, for that common interest, that all men have in truth, I am content to put this work upon a publick triall,
<pb facs="tcp:207311:8"/>in hope that I shall either be better confirmed in mine own opinion, by the approbation of others, whose judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēts I may better build on then mine own, or meet with so much ingenuous charitie in some, as meekly to make mee understand wherein I have er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and to direct me better.</p>
            <p>The way of truth is that I seek, but whether I have found it already my self, or shall hereafter be shewed it by another is not so much materiall. I would not willingly either like error any thing the better, because it is homeborn, nor truth the worse, because it comes to me as a stranger from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place. Which indifferency that I may not be drawn from but, as far as I can, keep my self free from any personall engagement. I am bold to put on the borrowed name of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Irenaeus Philalethes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:207311:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Sabbato-Dominica:</hi> A FEW PROPOSITIONS tending to reconcile the seeming Difference between the Letter of the Law and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian <hi>Libertie, in the Doctrine of the</hi> SABBATH and LORDS-DAY, briefly propounded, explained, and confirmed.</head>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <head>The first Proposition.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fourth <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in the literall sence and meaning of it doth designe a <hi>seventh day</hi> in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion onely, not the <hi>seventh day</hi> in order, also to be unto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:207311:9"/>of God the ordinarie time of holy rest.</p>
               <p>By the literall sense and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> I understand that interpretation of the words which according to the rules of <hi>Grammaticall</hi> instruction they may, and in analogie to other places of Scripture, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon received principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion they must bear.</p>
               <p>By a <hi>seventh day</hi> in proportion onely, not the <hi>seventh day</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; also I understand one day of <hi>seven</hi> indefinitely taken, not speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally restrained, in respect of order unto this or that <hi>seventh:</hi> account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from one onely fixed period, but so left at liberty that it may indifferently be understood of any of the <hi>seven,</hi> first or last, or second, third, fourth, fifth or sixth, to be reckoned from that one prefixed period. As in other cases, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.13. <hi>Two tenth deals of fine flower,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:207311:9"/>and the fourth par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of an Hin▪</hi> And <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.31. the fifth part of the tythes must needs be understood of such a proportion, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>tenth,</hi> a <hi>fourth</hi> a <hi>fifth,</hi> without any respect unto order at all; so as to imply that it must of necessitie be this or that <hi>tenth, fourth</hi> or <hi>fifth:</hi> for if it were any part at all of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion it was sufficient.</p>
               <p>By the people of God I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand all those, and onely those, who by profession of the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion take upon them to be in speciall covenant with the true God: for unto all those and onely unto those, I take the Law of the two Tables to be given by God at Mount <hi>Sinai:</hi> not unto the Nation of the <hi>Israelites</hi> alone, nor unto all mankind universally, but indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely onely unto all, as all had an unconfined liberty to become <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> by profession before the birth of Christ, and Christians af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:207311:10"/>and so to enter into speciall covenant with God, as the <hi>Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> had done before the Law was published. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5. &amp;c. (See the <hi>Appendix</hi> in the first exception and the answer to it.)</p>
               <p>By the ordinarie time of <hi>holy rest,</hi> I understand that sufficient and convenient part of time which nature it self, being ruled by right reason, will confesse, ought usually to be set apart for the solemne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of those actions of religious service, which are to be performed unto the true God by them that would have and shew that they have him to be their God in their lives and conversations.</p>
               <p>The Proposition thus explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I confirm it thus.</p>
               <p>The fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> in the litterall sence and meaning of it, doth designe either a <hi>seventh day</hi> in proportion onely, and not the <hi>seventh day</hi> in order also to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:207311:10"/>the people of God, the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie time of <hi>holy rest,</hi> or the <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day</hi> in order onely, and not a <hi>seventh day</hi> in proportion also, or both a <hi>seventh day</hi> in proportion, and the <hi>seventh day</hi> in order also. But not the <hi>second</hi> nor the <hi>third, ergo</hi> the first.</p>
               <p>The <hi>major</hi> is evident of it self. For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>dies septimus, Exod.</hi> 20.10. indifferently signifies a <hi>seventh day,</hi> or the <hi>seventh day, (a)</hi> and <hi>(the)</hi> whereby the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is expressed being particles proper to our English tongue, to which there is neither in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, nor the Latine, nor perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture in most other languages any thing answerable: which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the Schools supply by distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing of <hi>dies septimus formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and <hi>dies septimus materialiter.</hi> And though we should give an emphasis unto the Article <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and read it <hi>dies ille septimus, that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:207311:11"/>day</hi> (which no necessitie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth us to do, unlesse withall we take our selves tyed to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate in the next verse <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los illos,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>terram illam, those heavens,</hi> and <hi>that earth,</hi> as though there were some other heavens and another earth, which were not made in the six dayes but in some other) yet no shift what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will serve us to evade the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of this truth, that either it must be understood of a <hi>seventh</hi> in proportion onely, or the <hi>seventh</hi> in order onely, or both: for <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion</hi> and <hi>order</hi> must needs be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther joyned or severed in the sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>septimus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>minor</hi> consisteth of two parts: whereof the former that the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall sence and meaning of it doth not designe the <hi>seventh day</hi> in order onely, and not a <hi>seventh day</hi> in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion also, will easily, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:207311:11"/>be granted: for otherwise that <hi>seventh</hi> joyned with the other <hi>six</hi> should either exceed or come short of the whole: unlesse we will say that every <hi>seventh day</hi> is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther longer or shorter then some of the other six: or that the whole revolution of time may not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture account be measured by weeks, whereof every one hath neither more nor lesse but seven equall dayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece; if not in exact Astronomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll computation, yet at least in ordinary vulgar account. The B. of <hi>Ely, pag.</hi> 177. observeth that the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> made one day of seven a weekly Sabbath: and <hi>pag.</hi> 179. he saith, the subject of that <hi>Commandment</hi> is a naturall day of 24. houres.</p>
               <p>The latter part of the <hi>minor</hi> that the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> in the literall sence and meaning of it doth not designe both a <hi>seventh
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207311:12"/>day</hi> in proportion, and the <hi>seventh day</hi> in order also, to be unto the people of God the ordinary time of <hi>holy rest,</hi> is that which alone, I suppose, will be denied; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore onely needs to be confirmed. And to that pupose I would argue thus.</p>
               <p>That interpretation which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth the common and naturall equitie of the <hi>Commandment,</hi> which obligeth all the people of God to the end of the world, and nothing else is the literall sence and meaning of the <hi>Commandment</hi> if the <hi>Grammaticall</hi> construction of the words will bear it, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force no more. But that interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation wherein the fourth <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> is taken to designe a <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day</hi> in proportion onely, and not the <hi>seventh day</hi> in order also, to be unto the people of God the ordinary time of <hi>holy rest,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth the common and naturall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:207311:12"/>equitie of the <hi>Commandment,</hi> which obligeth all Gods people to the end of the world, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else: and the <hi>Grammaticall</hi> construction of the words will bear it, and enforce no more. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>major</hi> I presume will not be denied. (See the Appendix in the second exception, and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to it.)</p>
               <p>The <hi>minor</hi> consisteth of two parts. For proofe of the former, <hi>viz.</hi> that that Interpretation wherein the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> is taken to designe a <hi>seventh day</hi> in proportion onely, and not the <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day</hi> in order also, to be unto the people of God the ordinarie time of <hi>holy rest,</hi> includeth the common and naturall equitie of the <hi>Commandment,</hi> which obligeth all Gods people to the end of the world, and nothing else; I referre me to the reverend and very learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed L. B. of <hi>Ely,</hi> in his Treatise of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207311:13"/>the Sabbath &amp; Lords day, whose words are these, <hi>pag.</hi> 120. <hi>The common and naturall equitie of this Commandment obligeth mankinde to the end of the world.</hi> And <hi>pa</hi> 121. <hi>the equitie of the fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is of the law of Nature.</hi> And <hi>pag.</hi> 90. <hi>the common and naturall equitie of that Commandment is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: viz.</hi> that Gods people are obliged to observe a convenient and sufficient time for publick and solemne divine worsh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p, and for religious and Ecclesiasticall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And abstinence from secular labour and negotiation, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holy one day of every week for mans temporall and naturall refreshing, and for the spirituall good of his soul is very agreeable both to naturall and religious equitie; and it is grounded upon the ancient custome and practise of Gods people in time of the Law. Where in the Margent he quotes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:207311:13"/>out of <hi>Chrysostome in Genes. Hom.</hi> 10. <hi>Jam hinc ab initio doctrinam hanc insinuat nobis Deus, erudiens in circulo hebdomadae diem unum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrum,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Consecrare &amp; designare operationi spiritualium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which passage of <hi>Chrysostome</hi> appears unto me to intimate more then the Bishop seemeth to take notice of: <hi>viz.</hi> that the ancient custome and practise of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in keeping holy one day of every week was taught them by God even from the beginning. Which if it be true, and the thing in it self very agreeable both to naturall and religious equitie, as the B. confesseth, I do notsee what colour of reason any man can have to pretend it ceremoniall, or pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly appropriated in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> unto the Israelites a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: unlesse he will say, that what was generally intended unto all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207311:14"/>men before, was afterward in the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly limited, and restrained unto the Israelites alone; which he that will pretend to be true of the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> me thinks must be forced to confesse as true of all the other nine.</p>
               <p>And whereas he pretendeth that our keeping holy now one day of every week is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ancient custome and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of Gods people in time of the Law, I demand whether that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome and practise it self were not grounded either upon a Law of Nature, or at least upon a positive Law of divine institution: and if so (as I think it cannot be denied) why the keeping holy now of one day in every week should rather be said to be grounded upon that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome and practise, then upon that Law whether naturall or positive on which that custome and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207311:14"/>it self at first was grounded. Since it is not safe grounding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any custome or practise how common or ancient soever, unlesse that custome and practise it self be grounded upon such a foundation either in reason or Religion as still stands in force as wel for the latter as the former practise. Otherwise I do not see but that a <hi>Turke</hi> might plead as well for his circumcision, as grounded upon the ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome and practise of Gods people in time of the Law, as a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an for his keeping holy one day of every week, as grounded upon the like custome and practise, unlesse this custome and practise of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holy one day in every week were it self grounded on a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of another nature then that of circumcision was.</p>
               <p>Again, in that passage of the B. I observe that he makes that to be the common and naturall equitie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:207311:15"/>of the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> which I ever conceived to belong unto the first. For the first <hi>Com.</hi> requiring that we should have the true God to be our God, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our minds and in our hearts, but likewise in our lives and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versations (which must be by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming unto him not onely sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and occasionall, but likewise set and solemne actions of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous service, as I presume will not be denied) requires withall that a sufficient and convenient time should be set apart and employed to that purpose: since mens acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, especially externall, cannot at all be performed but in time and place, nor as they ought to be, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse that time and place be both sufficient and convenient. So that if this were all that the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> required of Gods people in requiring this, it should require no more then in effect the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:207311:15"/>first <hi>Commandment</hi> had done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, nor give any further dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction concerning the time to be employed in solemne worship, then might as well be understood concerning the place wherein that worship ought to be performed, which yet it is evident that it hath done. And I thinke I may adde that it was requisite it should be so: that so I may answer their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that ask a reason why God should rather designe a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of time then of place for his so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne service. Although such a question me thinks should need no answer, since it either is or at least should be enough for us that God hath done so: yet this we may conceive to be some reason of it. First, because time is a more inse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable circumstance of any acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then place can be. <hi>Moses</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing the creation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. begins with the beginning of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:207311:16"/>time, and so proceeds according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: he saith not where, but when each thing was done: even place it self can have no being but in time. Secondly, because one and the same proportion of time may be observed by Gods people eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where in performing the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne actions of religious service, whether publickly or privately, but one and the same proportion of place cannot. Thirdly, because there are general divisions of time into distinct proportions made by God himself even in the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and first constitution of time, the characters whereof stand stamped in the course of nature, by which even naturall reason may be guided in the choice of a suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and convenient part to be employed in solemne worship, as we shall have occasion to consider more anon. But there are no such divisions of place which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:207311:16"/>proportionable to the thing that is placed, and differs accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the various circumstances of the same.</p>
               <p>Besides, if this, and this onely be the common and naturall equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> that a sufficient and convenient time should be employed in holy worship, as it is pretended; I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand whether purposely intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and expressed in the words, or onely presupposed, and taken for granted. If purposely intended, and expressed; I demand whether in a phrase of speech that is to be understood properly or tropical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. If properly, then it doth not onely expresse the necessity of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving a sufficient and convenient time, but likewise shew plainly what part of time is sufficient and convenient, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>seventh day,</hi> one day in every week. If tropically, I demand what kind of trope it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:207311:17"/>can be, wherein the generall may so be understood by the speciall, as that the speciall it self must not be necessarily included in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. For if by the Sabbath day or a <hi>seventh day</hi> in the fourth <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> be intended a sufficient and convenient time, we must ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deny that a <hi>seventh day</hi> is a sufficient and convenient time, or else acknowledge it therein requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as that which is presupposed to be the common and naturall equitie of the <hi>Commandment:</hi> which will appear more plainly to be so, if we can prove that there is no other part of time which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will acknowledge to be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and convenient, but onely one day in every week, as anon I shall assay to do. If onely presup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, and taken for granted, I see not why we should esteem it more proper to the fourth <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> then to the <hi>second</hi> or the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:207311:17"/>
                  <hi>third:</hi> or why we should not as well esteeme the other necessarie duties of the <hi>first,</hi> as that we must have a God, and that the true God to be our God, that we must know him, love him, fear him, and obey him, and the like, to be the common and naturall equitie of the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> (for all these must needs be therein pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>supposed, and taken for granted) and so in the end reduce them all to one, without any distinction, except it be in such particulars onely as we resolve to reject at our pleasures, as not appertaining un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us but to the <hi>Israelites</hi> alone. (See the <hi>Appendix</hi> in the third Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and the <hi>Answer</hi> to it.)</p>
               <p>Again, I observe that the B. in that passage joynes publick and solemne worship together, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise religious and Ecclesiasticall duties; as though these were termes of equall extent, or that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:207311:18"/>Gods people were equally obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to them all by one and the same morall Law. Which I take to be a common errour, and the occasion of many mistakes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them that have written upon this subject. For all solemne divine worship is not publick, nor are all religious duties Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. And as it is one thing to be exercised and employed in the solemne actions of religious ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice simply considered, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing to be exercised and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the same solemne acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of religious service as they are publick and Ecclesiasticall: so the bond whereby Gods people are obliged to be so exercised and employed, must be referred unto divers <hi>Commandments.</hi> For the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne actions of religious service simply considered to the first <hi>Com.</hi> as before, for the publick and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall exercise and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207311:18"/>of them, if directed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired immediately by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, as amongst the Israelites in many things it was unto the first <hi>Commandment</hi> likewise, wherein generally all obedience unto God himself is enjoyned: if immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately depending upon the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Civill and Ecclesiasticall Governors, as now adayes it doth unto the first <hi>Commandment.</hi> As for the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> I conceive that the scope thereof is no more, but onely in a speciall manner to designe that proportion of time which is ordinarily to be employed by Gods people in so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne worship; and to give a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall intimation of the use and end unto which that time must be employed.</p>
               <p>And in that respect I conceive the B. expression not to be so full as it might have been, when he saith, that the keeping holy one
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207311:19"/>day in every week is very agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto naturall and religious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: having said before that Gods people are obliged by the common and naturall equitie of the <hi>Commandment</hi> which is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, to observe a sufficient and convenient time for solemne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship: for upon that ground I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it may be probably at least pretended, that naturall and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious equitie will not onely allow of that practise as fitting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, but likewise avow it for requisite and necessarie: as if to that purpose one should argue thus.</p>
               <p>If naturall equitie oblige men of necessity to observe a sufficient and convenient time for solemne worship; then naturall equitie must presuppose men able to judge of the time to be so observed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be sufficient &amp; convenient or no: otherwise naturall equitie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:207311:19"/>shall bind men to do that, which whether they have done or no they cannot tell, &amp; so they shall not be a law unto themselves, or their cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science witnes with them, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unto that of the Apostle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15. And naturall equitie cannot presuppose men able to judge of the time to be observed for solemne worship, whether it be sufficient and convenient or no, but upon this supposition, that either it must be all time abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, or a part of time onely. The former I presume will not be pretended agreeable unto naturall and religious equitie, I therefore let it passe. If the latter, it must be a part of time, either once onely to be chosen and observed, or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. The former I likewise pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume will not be pretended agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto naturall and religious equitie, and therefore I let that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so passe. If the latter, it must be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:207311:20"/>such a part of time as arises upon an arbitrary artificiall divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of time, which man himself at his own pleasure hath been or may be author of: or else such a part of time as arises upon a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall division of time which God himself made at the creation; the characters whereof are written in the course of nature: out of the parts whereof, if any one be taken and employed for solemne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, it will ordinarily be suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and convenient.</p>
               <p>Not the former, but the latter. For the generall determination of a common and naturall equitie which obligeth all mankind must needs depend upon something in nature, of as early an originall, as large an extent, as unchangeable constancie, and long continuance as it self. But no artificiall arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary division of time can be coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall unto that common and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:207311:20"/>equitie, which in this case is to be determined by it, neither so universally known, or perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly immutable, and consequently certain as that which is naturall. So that either there must be some such certain division of time appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent unto nature, or nature will never be able of it selfe to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether such or such a time be sufficient and convenient to be ordinarily employed in the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne actions of religious service or no.</p>
               <p>The maine things then to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in this case are: First, what naturall divisions of time there are, the characters whereof were at the beginning, even in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by God himself the Creator, imprinted in the course of nature. Secondly, which of those divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons it is that common and naturall equitie being called unto counsell, must needs acknowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:207311:21"/>doth afford a sufficient and convenient time to be employed in solemne worship.</p>
               <p>For the first, it is evident both by the history of the Creation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. and 2. and by the observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of art and experience, that there are foure main divisions of time which God himselfe hath made, namely, into dayes, into weeks, into moneths, and into yeers: whereof the second and the third arise out of the multiplied revolution of the first and the last of the third.</p>
               <p>Here nothing, I suppose, will be denied or doubted of, at least there is nothing that concerns our present purpose much, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the division of time into weeks, whereof every one consists of seven dayes apiece, be a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall division of Gods own institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Creation the chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters whereof may be observed in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:207311:21"/>the course of nature. For the affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative whereof, I doubt not but I might produce the unanimous consent both of Fathers, School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Interpreters upon <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis</hi> the first and second, as these few particulars which I have had opportunity to take notice of, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade me to beleeve.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Basil. in Hexam. hom.</hi> 2. <hi>Deus sane qui temporis naturam creavit, mensuras ipsi ac signa, nimirum spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia dierum adjunxit, septimanaque ipsum metiens, in orbem septimanam in sese semper versari jussit, curricu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la temporis ac motiones enumeran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem: &amp; unum item diem septimanam conficere, ipsum in sese septies rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lactan. de divino premio Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Dies septem sunt. qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus per vicem revolutis orbes conficiuntur annorum, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clem. Alex. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Strom. In sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenariis totus mundus circumagitur
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:207311:22"/>omnium quae &amp; viva gignuntur, &amp; quae nascuntur, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieron. in Amos, cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Septena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium numerum esse sanctum etiam Sabbatum probat, in quo requievit Deus ab omnibus operibus suis— Novit &amp; hoc secularis philosophia &amp; medicorum libri — ita ab initio mundi diebus conditis, ut omnes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bores &amp; molestiae septimo numero conquiescant—&amp; septem astra jux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta numerum dierum dicuntur erran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>August. ad Casulan. Epa.</hi> 86. <hi>Septem dies sunt, qui volumine tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum per sua vestigia revocantur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Id. de Genesi ad literam, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 18. <hi>Dies septimus &amp; ipse unus est dierum, qui omnes septem sunt, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum repetitione menses &amp; anni &amp; secula peraguntur: ut mane quod po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neretur post vesperam septimi hoc esset initium octavi diei, de quo jam deinceps silendum fuit, quia idem primus est ad quem reditur, à quo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:207311:22"/>rursus hebdo madis serìes ordiatur. Vnde probabilius est istos quidem septem dies illorum nominibus &amp; nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero alios atque alios sibimet succe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes currendo temporalia peragere spatia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lomb. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>sent. dist.</hi> 15. <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merando dies usque ad septimum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedimus, &amp; dicimus septem esse dies, quorum repetitione omne tempus agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And peradventure much more might be added to this purpose out of their observations, that are expert in Astronomie, Astrologie, and Chronologie, as I am induced to conceive by that of <hi>Jos. Scalig. Can. Isagog. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. whose words are these. <hi>Vtimur hebdomade dierum, non ogdoade, ut prisci Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani, neque Triscaedecade, ut Mexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cani. Nam secundum illa instituta aliae periodi excogitandae essent, quae omnino cum veris rationibus tropicis nunquam quadrare possunt, ut hinc
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:207311:23"/>occultam quandam vim septenarii dierum agnoscere possis.</hi> And a little after: <hi>Divinitus igitur institutus est numerus dierum septenarius, qui ad omnem civilis anni solaris ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem commodissimus est, &amp;, ut dixi, nescio quid</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>habet.</hi> Mr. <hi>Purchas</hi> in his pilgrimage, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. in the Margin saith, The Heathen by the light of nature had their weeks, as appeareth by naming the dayes after the seven Planets, &amp;c. <hi>Aret. Probl de Sab.</hi> He further alledgeth to prove the observation of one day of seven in every week to be naturall and morall. <hi>Aquin. secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da secundae, q.</hi> 122. <hi>art</hi> 4. Mr. <hi>Hooker Eccles. Pol. lib.</hi> 5. §. 70. <hi>Broughton</hi> in his Concent. And <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. in the margin. <hi>Septimana res omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quidem orientis populis ab ultima usque antiquitate usitata nobis autem Europaeis vix tandem post Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nismum recepta. Scal. de Emendat. T. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Antiquior est appellatio die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:207311:23"/>septimanae sub nominibus</hi> 7. <hi>pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netarum quam horarum. Horae nova appellatio à Graecis, Cor. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp; Casaub. ad Athen. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>aliquanto post Aristotelis tempora.</hi> Which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legations of his may give just oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of further enquirie unto those that are furnished with meanes and opportunities that way. See the Appendix in the fourth Exception, and the Answer to it.</p>
               <p>For the second, men cannot make perfecter divisions of time then God himself hath made; and of these which he hath made if nature be put to determine out of which a sufficient and convenient part must be taken, to be ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly employed in the solemne acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of religious service, she cannot but acknowledge that of necessity it must be either a day out of a week, or a day out of a moneth, or a moneth out of a yeer.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:207311:24"/>
               <p> Now as the first naturall divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of time is into dayes; so the first naturall multiplication of daies is into weeks. And these two divisions of time are alwayes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, one naturall day or weeke being never either longer or shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then another (understanding it of those dayes and weeks which are measured <hi>per motum diurnum totius,</hi> if we speak either according unto exact Astronomicall compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or otherwise according unto ordinarie vulgar account) whereas moneths and yeers are sometimes forced to admit or loose odde minutes, houres, or dayes to keep their courses even in account. For that those two dayes whereof we read, <hi>Jos.</hi> 10. and <hi>Isa.</hi> 38. in length exceeded others, was not naturall, but mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, and extraordinarie: and therefore in the ordinatie compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of time they must passe in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:207311:24"/>the same rank with other dayes. And larger then one day of seven there is no part of time arising up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a naturall division, because the least naturall proportion of time that ariseth upon a multiplied re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of dayes is a week. Lesse then one day in a week then which is a <hi>seventh day</hi> in proportion, will not be allowed by the judgement of nature it selfe, as sufficient to be employed in the solemne acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of religious service. For I do not expect it should be pretended agreeable either unto naturall or religious equitie, that a lesse part is sufficient for God, when a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may more conveniently be had. But a day out of a moneth, or a moneth out of a yeer, would neither be convenient nor equall. Not convenient, because the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities both of religious and worldly affaires do equally require a mutuall enterchange of speedier
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:207311:25"/>dispatches, and quicker returnes. Not equall, because sometimes they must either be extended or contracted above ordinarie, or else the whole account of time put out of frame.</p>
               <p>And so I have done with the former part of my <hi>minor, viz.</hi> that that interpretation wherein the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> is taken to designe a <hi>seventh day</hi> in proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on onely, and not the <hi>seventh day</hi> in order also, to be unto the people of God the ordinarie time of holy rest, includeth the common and naturall equitie of the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which obligeth all Gods people to the end of the world, and nothing else.</p>
               <p>This onely let me adde, that when I speak of naturall equitie, I do not intend to acknowledge that equitie alone for naturall, which dim eyed nature, now in the state of corruption, can easily discover
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:207311:25"/>to be such: but if there be any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther equitie, which nature in its pure estate of innocence could of it self have seene to be such, or which corrupted nature now not further blind folded by passion or prejudice, but willingly giving it self to be guided by the rules of right reason, must needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be such when it is disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and made known; I make account that that likewise may be esteemed naturall equitie. For I doubt not but straight lines would be straight, and naturally straight, though the naturall straightnesse of them could never be demonstrated unto us by any other meanes but onely by the use of artificiall instruments. And why may not many duties then be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie, naturally necessarie; the naturall necessitie whereof yet may not be now apparent unto us, but onely by divine discoverie?
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:207311:26"/>Is not according to the usuall say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Rectum</hi> onely <hi>index sui &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liqui?</hi> Can we know that we do well by any other means, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the same whereby we may likewise know whether we do ill or no? Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith of himself, <hi>I had not known sinne but by the Law: for I had not known lust, except the Law had said, thou shalt not covet. Rom.</hi> 7.7. And yet I suppose there is as much common naturall equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in this <hi>Commandment, Thou shalt not covet thy neighbours house; thou shalt not covet thy neighbours wife, &amp;c.</hi> as in any of the other five that went before it. Though marriage be an ordinance of God, the insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution whereof had never come unto our knowledge, if God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self had not conveighed it to us by his Word. Certainly divine dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverie by revealed light serves not onely to impose a necessitie of obedience where it was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:207311:26"/>but likewise sometimes to informe us what necessarie du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties nature it selfe would have taught us, that we stood obliged unto, had we and it continued still in our primevall state of integritie. The true God is not known unto us now to be such as he is, but by revealed light, nor can be served as he ought to be, but onely by those that are instructed by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self: shall we therefore pretend that naturall equitie doth not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige all men unto the knowledge and service of the true God: Sure if we do, we may as well pretend, that either there is no naturall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie at all in any thing; or that by naturall equitie we are not obliged to do any thing at all: for if the knowledge and service of the true God be not necessarie, nothing is. Therefore me thinks it cannot be safe to exclude all those out of the number of naturall duties, which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:207311:27"/>nature now cannot see to be such without revealed light. For by that meanes, I suppose, we should make it a difficult matter to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince a gain sayer of a naturall necessitie in any kind of duty what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever. For whatever we could propound as a principle in nature, to ground the necessitie of a dutie upon, he might pretend it none of natures owne, but borrowed: should we point him to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of the same, be it justice, mercie, chastitie, sobrietie, or any other morall dutie exactly obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by meer heathen men, might he not pretend that they did that in imitation of the <hi>Israelites,</hi> unto whom were committed the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God, as well as that from them they borrowed their sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and their solemne Feast dayes? Should we urge him with the testimonies of the most anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Heathen Authors; might he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:207311:27"/>not as easily reply, that <hi>Moses</hi> wrote before them all, and that they might learne other things as well as the histories of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the Flood from him? Should we presse him with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of barbarous Nations, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unacquainted with let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and learning, whereby either the Laws or manners of other men might be conveighed unto their knowledge; might he not except against that evidence in some, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse we our selves would yeeld to accept the same from him in all other particulars? why may not these evasions serve a ruffians turn to shift himselfe from under the yoke of other <hi>Commandments,</hi> as well as reverend Divines make use of the same, or the like, to put by the force of arguments urged for the sanctification of one day in every week, as a necessarie dutie grounded on the fourth <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:207311:28"/>We read not that <hi>Sampson</hi> thought himselfe any thing the lesse obliged to perform the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the covenant he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into with his thirtie compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, because he could truly say unto them: <hi>If ye had not ploughed with my heifer, ye had not found out my riddle. Judg.</hi> 14.18. And if God in his Word discover his will concerning any thing which he would have his people do, and upon that discovery they can find it to be agreeable unto naturall and religious equitie (as the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holy of one day in every week is acknowledged to be) although they neither did nor could of themselves conceive any such thing before, me thinks, their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture obligation should be nothing abated by their former ignorance. See the <hi>Appendix</hi> in the fifth Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and the Answer to it.</p>
               <p>Since then the sufficiency and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:207311:28"/>conveniency of that proportion of time, whereof wee speake, <hi>viz. a seventh day,</hi> or one day in every weeke, to be unto the people of God, the ordinary time of holy rest, is so sufficiently discovered unto them in the fourth <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> by God himselfe, that nature it selfe, I thinke, would be asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to acknowledge reason in any thing that should be pretended to the contrary. I durst not exclude the perpetuall observation of that proportion from the compasse of that common and naturall equitie, which obligeth all Gods people to the end of the world: although I should grant that without that discovery, nature now corrupted as it is, neither would nor could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have taken any notice of it. For I presume it might be well knowne to <hi>Adam</hi> in his state of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, though after his fall, I doubt not, but his knowledge in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:207311:29"/>that, as in other particulars, was much impaired, and though all his posteritie till <hi>Moses</hi> time, had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of it: which whether they did or no, I thinke is more then can be certainly evidenced by any one necessary Argument. And that <hi>Adam</hi> once did know it, I am the rather induced to beleeve because it is now acknowledged to be very agreeable, both unto naturall and religious equitie, and I can hardly be perswaded that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of that nature was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to <hi>Adam</hi> in his state of innocence, at least I thinke no man can prove this was.</p>
               <p>For the latter part of my <hi>Minor, viz.</hi> that the Grammaticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of the words will beare that interpretation, and inforce no more, it is evident, as before, in that <hi>dies septimus,</hi> indifferently sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, a seventh day in proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or the seventh day in order,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:207311:29"/>and unlesse other Arguments be brought to sway, it will incline no more unto the one translation then the other. And what better argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to that purpose can there be, then those that are drawne from analogie unto other places of Scripture, and the common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived principles of Religion? which I conceive, plead strongly for a seventh day in proportion onely, not for the seventh day in order also, accounting as I said at first, from some one fixed period onely. And to that purpose I would argue thus:</p>
               <p>That interpretation which agrees with the universall and perpetuall practise of Gods people, both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law and under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, recorded in Scripture, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directed or approved of by God himselfe, or the Ministers of God, inspired by the holy Ghost, holds better analogie with other
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:207311:30"/>places of Scripture, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon received principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, then that which differs from it.</p>
               <p>But that interpretation accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto which the fourth <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement</hi> is taken to designe a seventh day in proportion onely, not the seventh day in order also, to be unto the people of God the ordinary time of holy rest, agrees with the universall and perpetuall practise of Gods people, both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law and under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, recorded in Scripture, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directed or approved of by God himselfe, or the Ministers of God, inspired by the holy Ghost: and that interpretation according unto which the Commandement is taken, to designe both a seventh day in proportion, and the seventh day in order also differs from it: <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is grounded upon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:207311:30"/>these two, unlesse I mistake them, commonly received and undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted truths.</p>
               <p>First, That the Scriptures and the commonly received princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion, doe never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict themselves, or one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That the universall and perpetuall practise of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, both under the Law and under the Gospel, is agreeable both unto the Scriptures, and the commonly received principles of Religion: whence <hi>Praxis sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum est interpres praeceptorum,</hi> hath sometimes passed in the nature of a principle.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Minor,</hi> we know that the people of God, both under the law and under the Gospel, have obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a seventh day in proportion, <hi>viz.</hi> one day in every weeke, as the ordinary time of holy rest, but not the seventh day in order, also ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:207311:31"/>from one prefixed peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od onely, <hi>viz.</hi> not the self-same day in every weeke, but under the Law the last, and under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel the first. That wherein they all agree, is the same proportion of time; and that wherein they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, is the order of the time pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned. In this the practise of Gods people under the Law was directed and approved of by God himselfe: the practise of Gods people under the Gospel was, if not directed, yet at least approved of; if not by Christ himselfe, yet by his Apostles, infallibly assisted and directed by his holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>The Bishop of <hi>Ely,</hi> upon another occasion, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. of his Epistle Dedicatory, hath these words; <hi>The Apostles act was according to the Word, for they were men inspired by the holy Ghost.</hi> Whereupon I as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume. But the Apostles act was to observe a seventh day in proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:207311:31"/>on onely, not the seventh day in order also, as the ordinary time of holy rest: and there is no other word but this of the fourth <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,</hi> according unto which that act could be. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that it should seeme, what ever men doe now adayes, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles and primitive Churches understood the fourth <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to designe a seventh day in proportion onely, not the seventh day in order also, to be unto the people of God the ordinary time of holy rest. For if it had been as peculiarly proper to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> to set apart a seventh day in proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the ordinary time of holy fest, as it was to set apart that se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day in order, which they did. The Apostles and the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Churches would have found the self-same necessitie of altering the proportion of the time, as the order of the time proportioned:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:207311:32"/>which since they did not, it seemes they saw no reason why they should. And certainly, if the fourth <hi>Commandement</hi> in the self-same word, designed both, and God did purposely intend that his people should so understand it, either both must be ceremoniall or neither, whereof the former is directly overthrowne by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise, the other, by the doctrine of the Christian Churches.</p>
               <p>And hereupon it followes.</p>
               <p>First, That the fourth <hi>Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement</hi> is neither rightly interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nor understood by them that take it in the literall sense &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, to designe one definite or speciall day of every weeke, as the first, second, third, fourth, fift, sixt, or last in order from some one prefixed period, to be unto the people of God the ordinary time of holy rest.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That Saturday was
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:207311:32"/>no more the Sabbath of the fourth <hi>Commandement</hi> unto the Jewes, then Sunday is to Christians.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That the designation of that one definite or speciall day in every weeke, whereon the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath should be kept, both then was, and still is <hi>juris positivi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, that the reason why the <hi>Jewes</hi> observed Saturday for their Sabbath, and Christians Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day for theirs, is not to be found, and so not to be sought in the fourth <hi>Commandement.</hi> See the Appendix in the sixt exception, and the Answer to it.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, That Jewish supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, so farre as concernes the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary time of holy rest, is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently avoyded, and Christian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie asserted, by fixing it upon another day in order, although of the same proportion.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, That the testimonies urged to evince the observation
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:207311:33"/>of the Sabbath, now unlawfull, as that which was proper to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> must be understood of the Sabbath, not as it was a seventh day in proportion onely, but the seventh day in order also from that fixed period, at which the <hi>Jewes</hi> began their first account of weeks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:207311:33"/>
               <head>The second Proposition.</head>
               <head type="sub">The fourth Commandment in the literall sense and meaning of it, is simply and perpetually Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, aswell as the second, third, fift, sixt, seventh, eighth, and ninth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the literall sense and meaning of the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, as in the first pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, that interpretation of the words, whereby they are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood to designe a seventh day in proportion onely, not the seventh day in order also, to be unto the people of God the ordinary time of holy rest.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:207311:34"/>
               <p> By <hi>simply and perpetually morall,</hi> I understand such a Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as wherein that which is commanded, is in its own intrinse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call nature and qualitie good, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is or may be resolved into some dictate or principle of the Law of nature, imprinted in mans heart at the creation, obliging all Gods people to universall &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall obedience, both in regard of persons, times, and places. See the Appendix in the seventh Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and the answer to it.</p>
               <p>I instance the second, third, fift, sixth, seventh, eight, and ninth Commandements, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king mention of the first and last, because I take the first and last Commandements, to comprise in generall all the duties of piety and charitie, which Gods people owe immediately to God himselfe, and mediately to God in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and the other eight to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:207311:34"/>so many severall branches of obedience, three in the first, and five in the second Table, which God would have his people in a speciall manner to take notice of: all which may be reduced unto as generally they are included in the other two, the first and last.</p>
               <p>The proposition thus explained, I confirme it thus:</p>
               <p>That Commandement in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall sense and meaning of it, is simply and perpetually morall, as well as the second, third, fift, sixt, seventh, eight, and ninth, which neither in the matter delivered, nor manner of delivery, doth any way differ more from them then they doe each from one another, but hath the characters of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, simply and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally morall, appertaining unto it as well as they. But the fourth <hi>Commandement,</hi> in the literall sense and meaning of it, doth neither in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:207311:35"/>the matter delivered, nor manner of delivery, any way differ more from the second, third, fift, sixt, seventh, eight, and ninth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, then they doe each from one another: but hath the characters of a Commandement simply and perpetually morall, appertaining unto it as well as they, <hi>Ergo:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Major</hi> I take to be evident of it selfe. For if it be not, it must either have some speciall marke and stampe set upon it, either in the matter delivered, or manner of delivery, whereby Gods people may be able to distinguish be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween it and the rest, or some ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse testimony, speaking plainly to that purpose. But there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sentence, nor word, nor sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor tittle in the whole booke of God, that intimates any thing at all to this purpose, that of the ten Commandements uttered by
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:207311:35"/>God himselfe on Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and writ with his owne finger in the two Tables, nine alone were sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and perpetually morall, one and that the fourth onely positive and ceremoniall. Either therefore we must finde some difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Commandments them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, or else wee can have no ground to fix the foot of a distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction on: and to distinguish where there is no difference, is a more likely meanes to maske an errour, then unfold a truth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> consisteth of three parts: the first concernes the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter delivered in the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: the second, the manner of delivery: the third, the characters of a Commandement simply and perpetually morall.</p>
               <p>For the first, I take the matter delivered in the fourth <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to be as before in the first proposition, nothing else but the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:207311:36"/>designation of a seventh day, in proportion onely, to be unto the people of God the ordinary time of holy rest. And in doing this, the fourth <hi>Commandement</hi> doth differ no more from the rest of the Commandements, then they doe each from one another: for each of the rest hath its speciall object proper to it selfe, as well as the fourth: and there is no more diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between <hi>Remember the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day to keepe it holy,</hi> and, <hi>Thou shalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vaine:</hi> then there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Honour thy father and thy mother,</hi> and, <hi>Thou shalt not commit adultery.</hi> And I shall take it for granted of the rest, untill I see some instance given to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>For the second, I take it to be out of question, and that no man will deny, but that the fourth <hi>Commandement</hi> was delivered in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:207311:36"/>the self-same manner with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nine.</p>
               <p>For the third, if we take but those three characters of a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> simply and perpetually morall, which are laid down by the Bishop of <hi>Ely, pag.</hi> 28, 29, 30, 31. for ought I perceive they all appertain as well unto the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> as to the rest. The fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> requiring no more in the literall sence and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, as was formerly shewed in the first Proposition; but that which nature it selfe may either observe, or at least acknowledge to be in its own inward nature and qualitie good, yea necessarie to be observed by all Gods people at all times, and in all places. And the exception which the Bishop in the pages following takes to the morality of the fourth <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</hi> by application of those characters is onely in respect of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:207311:37"/>the <hi>seventh day</hi> in order, which he takes to be the literall and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular object of the <hi>Commandment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if the first Proposition stand fast, that the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> in the literall sence and meaning of it doth designe a <hi>seventh day</hi> in proportion onely, not the <hi>seventh day</hi> in order also, to be unto the people of God the ordinarie time of <hi>holy rest,</hi> this second will of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity follow, that the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> in the literall sence and meaning of it is simply and perpetually morall, as well as the second, third, fifth, sixth, seventh, eight and ninth. For in so doing, the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> doth as the rest expresse no more but that which Gods people, by the light of their naturall understanding, might either observe, or at least acknowledge to be beseeming or good for them to do: and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever may possibly be known to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:207311:37"/>be of that qualitie doth bind men absolutely as they are men: as Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> speaks. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. §. 8.9.10.</p>
               <p>And hence it follows.</p>
               <p>First, That they who deny the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> in the literal sence and meaning of it, to be sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and perpetually morall, may be justly suspected to hold no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opinion of the rest.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That they who esteeme themselves not bound by vertue of the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> to set apart one day in every week for the ordinarie time of <hi>holy rest,</hi> may think themselves as well at libertie to make images of God, and worship him therein, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:207311:38"/>
               <head>The third Proposition.</head>
               <head type="sub">If the Jews were necessarily bound to exercise or abstaine from any thing upon the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terday, which Christians are not upon the Sunday, it was not by virtue of the fourth Commandment, but by some other positive Law.</head>
               <p>BY the <hi>Saterday,</hi> I understand that day which the <hi>Jews</hi> set apart for their ordinarie time of holy rest: not as designed in the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> but as that whereunto they were directed by the voice of God himselfe, before the Law was published upon Mount <hi>Sinai;</hi> taking occasion from that speciall act of his providence, wherby he so disposed that <hi>Manna</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:207311:38"/>wherewith he fedde them in the wildernesse, should faile to fall upon that day. <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.22. &amp;c. Which day is generally concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be the <hi>seventh</hi> in order from the Creation: and some undertake to prove it so: as <hi>Joh Behm. Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolog. Manuduct. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 3. But the arguments he urgeth to that purpose, are such as have greater need of proofe themselves then the conclusion he infers upon them; being but borrowed from that which I conceive to be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon errour: <hi>viz</hi> that the sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the <hi>seventh day</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.3. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.11. was purposely intended unto it, as well in respect of order as propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And whether the day which the <hi>Jews</hi> observed for their <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> were the <hi>seventh</hi> in order from the Creation, or no, it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not, if, as before in the first Proposition, the fourth <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:207311:39"/>do designe a <hi>seventh day</hi> in proportion onely; not the <hi>seventh day</hi> in order also, to be unto the people of God the ordinarie time of <hi>holy rest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the <hi>Sonday,</hi> I understand that day which Christians set apart for their ordinarie time of <hi>holy rest:</hi> not as designed in the fourth <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</hi> but as that whereunto they have been guided by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of the Apostles and primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Churches: who were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in directed at the first, if not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by Christ himself, yet at least by that holy Spirit where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were inspired, taking occasion from that act of Gods providence, whereby he so dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, that Christ should rise again from the dead that day. Which that it was the first day in order of the week, accounting the <hi>Sater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> whereupon the <hi>Jews</hi> observed their <hi>Sabbath</hi> the last, is evident in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:207311:39"/>all the foure Evangelists: but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the first day in order from the Creation or no, untill it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved whether the <hi>Saterday</hi> were the <hi>seventh,</hi> is neither possible cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to know, nor any way ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to enquire.</p>
               <p>The proportion thus explained, follows necessarily upon the two former. For if the literall sence and meaning of the fourth <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> be no more but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe a <hi>seventh day</hi> in proportion onely, to be unto the people of God the ordinarie time of <hi>holy rest:</hi> and if in this sence and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> be simply and perpetually morall: then neither were the <hi>Jews</hi> by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> obliged to do any thing more, or Christians lesse, then to observe one day in <hi>seven</hi> as the ordinarie time of <hi>holy rest.</hi> That is one day in every week so to lay aside their
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:207311:40"/>usuall employment in civil affairs, that they may in a speciall manner then be exercised in the solemne actions of religious service; by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance whereof they may have, and make it appeare indeed, that they have the true God to be their God in their lives and conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>But what those actions are wherein Gods people must then in a solemne manner be exercised the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> meddles not with particularly, onely it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates they must be holy; and so makes a generall reference unto the first <hi>Commandment,</hi> wherein is required the actuall exercise of all those actions, by performance whereof we have, and shew that we have the true God to be our God in every kind, both in our minds and understandings, our hearts and affections, our lives and conversations.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:207311:40"/>
               <p> These actions of religious ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires all Gods people, when, and wheresoever in a speciall manner, to exercise and imploy themselves in one day in every week above the rest: and to that purpose on that day to lay aside their usuall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments upon other dayes, and so to order their affairs, that six dayes diligence in worldly busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse may sufficiently provide for the convenience of a <hi>seventh dayes</hi> rest, to be imployed in holy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship. And this is all that the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> either did or doth oblige the <hi>Jews</hi> or us unto.</p>
               <p>Other things the <hi>Jews</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned or forbidden to do upon their <hi>Sabbath</hi> the <hi>Saterday:</hi> as to have new bread put upon the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Tabernacle. <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.8. to have the continuall burnt-of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering and drink-offering doubled. <hi>Numb.</hi> 28.9, 10. to kindle any fire.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:207311:41"/>
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.3. But these and the like observances they stood obliged unto, not by vertue of the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> but by those other positive Laws which no more concern us Christians now, then the other ceremoniall and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Laws appendixes onely of the morall, and appropriated unto the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hence it follows,</p>
               <p>First, That the example of the <hi>Jews</hi> in the observation of their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> is no necessarie rule for Christians now to guide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by in the observation of theirs, unlesse it may be made to appeare that therein they did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what they were obliged to by virtue of the fourth <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, That the ground of obligation whereby Christians stand charged with sundrie parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, to be observed by them
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:207311:41"/>upon the <hi>Lords day,</hi> now must be drawn out of other <hi>commandments,</hi> and cannot be directly and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately deduced from the fourth. As that such or such a company of people are publickly to meet together upon the <hi>Lords day</hi> in such or such a place, so often or so sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; there to continue so long or so short a time in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of such or such actions of religious service, dependeth upon positive laws either Ecclesiasticall or Civill, of humane institution, unto which men owe obedience by virtue of the fift <hi>Commandment.</hi> Yet so that they by whose autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity those laws are enacted, are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited in generall by the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> what to require by those laws, <hi>viz.</hi> that which ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily may not hinder, but help to further the sanctification of the <hi>resting day.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:207311:42"/>
               <head>The fourth Proposition.</head>
               <head type="sub">To call the Sunday now the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, is no more to Judaize, then it is to call the Ministers of the Gospel Priests, the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist a Sacrifice, or the Cm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Table an Altar.</head>
               <p>BY the <hi>Sunday,</hi> I understand that day of the weeke which is by Christians now adayes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, as the ordinary time of holy rest, not simply in it selfe, but with relation to that use unto which it is put.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Judaizing,</hi> I understand to doe or say something, whereby we may be said to have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, or to partake with the <hi>Jewes</hi> in something so proper unto them, that thereby they have been, or
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:207311:42"/>may be, not unfitly distinguished from all other Nations or socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of men.</p>
               <p>By calling the Ministers of the Gospel <hi>Priests,</hi> the <hi>Eucharist</hi> a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> and the Communion Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an <hi>Altar,</hi> I understand the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected applying of those particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar names by Christians now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes to such persons and things, as in regard of their office and use, carry some correspondence and analogie unto other persons and things, unto which the same names were under the Law applyed by the <hi>Jewes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The proposition thus explained, I confirme it thus:</p>
               <p>To Judaize is unlawfull for Christians. But to call the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day now the Sabbath, is no more unlawfull for Christians, then to call the Ministers of the Gospel Priests, &amp;c. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Major</hi> I presume will not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:207311:43"/>be denyed. The <hi>Minor</hi> may be proved thus.</p>
               <p>That which is no more forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, is no more unlawfull. But to call the Sunday now the Sabbath, is no more forbidden, then to call the Table of the Lord an <hi>Altar,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, the originall use of names is to be significant, <hi>ad pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citum imponentis,</hi> and Christians have as much libertie and reason to use the word <hi>Sabbath,</hi> to signifie the Lords day, as the word <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> to signifie the Lords Supper. Or rather more, since the Lords day as now it is, or ought to be used amongst Christians, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly a Sabbath day, that is, a day of rest: but the Lords Supper, a memoriall onely of the death of Christ, as our ordinary <hi>Catechisme</hi> teacheth us to speake.</p>
               <p>Besides, to Judaize is to doe or say something, whereby wee may
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:207311:43"/>be said to have fellowship, or to partake with the <hi>Jewes</hi> in some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing proper unto them. But to call the Lords day the Sabbath, is not to doe that whereby wee may be said to partake with the <hi>Jewes</hi> in any thing proper unto them. For they never called the Lords day the Sabbath, but the Saturday: and they more partake with the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that call the Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the Sabbath now, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists and some others doe, then they that give that name unto the Lords day alone.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Jews</hi> gave that name unto their ordinary day of holy rest.</p>
               <p>Suppose they did: may not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers therfore give the same name unto another day of holy rest, and yet not Judaize? May not we call our Saviour Christ the Messias, because the <hi>Jews</hi> call him so, whom yet they expect to come to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:207311:44"/>be their Saviour? But the truth is, it was not the <hi>Jews</hi> themselves that put that name upon the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terday,</hi> their day of <hi>holy rest,</hi> but God himself taught them by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> to apply that name unto that day. <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.23. and in the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> hath put that name upon the ordinarie day of <hi>holy rest</hi> unto his people whensoever: one day in every week either is, or at least wise ought to be a Sabbath day, the Sabbath of the Lord. And our Saviour himself, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.8. speaking of his owne authoritie over the time to be employed in holy worship: and <hi>Mark.</hi> 2.27. speaking of all mens equall interest unto the use of it, refuses not the name of <hi>Sabbath,</hi> but saith, <hi>The Sonne of Man is Lord also of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</hi> And, <hi>The Sabbath was made for man, and not man for the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</hi> He doth not say, the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was made for you <hi>Jews</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:207311:44"/>and other men have nothing to do with it; but he speakes of man indefinitely, and that is as much in effect, as generally of all men. So <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.20. he biddeth his disciples pray that their flight be not on the <hi>Sabbath day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And why should we need to contend about names, if we agree concerning the things intended by those names? The proper name of that which is necessarie cannot be unlawfull. We agree that there must be amongst Gods people so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne times of holy rest: we agree that the ordinary time of holy rest to us is not the Saterday now, but the Sunday. Whether then is not the Sonday now a day of <hi>holy rest?</hi> or is not the name <hi>Sabbath</hi> a fit name for such a day? If the Sonday be not the ordinarie time of holy rest to us, either then we have none at all, or some other: If none at all, how can we be freed
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:207311:45"/>from a just imputation of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane impietie? If some other, then either that may beare the name of <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or else the name <hi>Sabbath</hi> is not a fit name for such a day: which none, me thinks, should dare to say, but he that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumes he can teach the holy Ghost to speak, who commonly cals all such dayes <hi>Sabbaths:</hi> and if it be a fit name for another day of the same nature, then why not for this? And it is a wonder to me how some men can find the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie observation of other holy dayes appointed by the Church and State, enjoyned by the name of Sabbaths, both in the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> and elsewhere in Scripture, and yet that it should be cried out against as Judaisme, when men speake of the Lords day by the same name. What if wee should call Sunday now the day of rest? were that any more
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:207311:45"/>to Judaize, then it were to rest that day? Is it Judaizing to use an Hebrew word of the same signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in stead of an English? why then should it not be heatheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing to use a Greeke or Latine word? Are not other Jewish names of times as Pentecost, and Pasche still in use? And were these any lesse, nay were they not more ceremoniall then the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Sabbath was? But those names have been anciently used; and the Sonday hath not been cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Sabbath till of late.</p>
               <p>Suppose that were true, as I presume it is not: may no names now adayes be used but those that have been heretofore? <hi>Horace</hi> was of another mind when he said:
<q>
                     <l>—Licuit semper{que} licebit,</l>
                     <l>Signatum presente nota producere nomen.</l>
                     <l>Ʋt sylvae foliis pronos mutantur in annos.</l>
                     <l>Prima cadunt ita verborum vetus interit</l>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:207311:46"/>
                     <l>Et juvenum ritu florent modo nata vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentque.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And,
<q>
                     <l>Multa renascentur quae jam cecidere ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentque.</l>
                     <l>Quae nunc sunt in honore vocabula si vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let usus.</l>
                     <l>Quem penes arbitrium est &amp; jus &amp; nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma loquendi.</l>
                  </q> Or if antiquitie alone have the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to grant a Warrant for the use of words; how is it that others are not branded for their upstart noveltie as well as this? For how many ages is it since the name <hi>Puritan</hi> hath been applyed unto such as being every way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable unto the doctrine and discipline established by publick Authoritie in the Church, do one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dissent from particular men in some private opinions?</p>
               <p>Put case the <hi>Lords day</hi> were not called the Sabbath heretofore: yet was it not called the <hi>resting
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:207311:46"/>day,</hi> if not in English, yet in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine? What else is the significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Latine word <hi>Feria,</hi> which they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have put instead of Sabbath, when to distinguish the other dayes of the week they set themselves of purpose to avoid both <hi>Jewish</hi> names and heathenish? Is it not granted, or at least may it not be proved that the ordinarie time of <hi>holy rest</hi> amongst Gods people was transferred from the Saterday to the Sunday? And why may not that then carry the name which came in the place? Why may not the <hi>Lords day</hi> be honoured by Christians with the name of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, as well as Christians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves are honoured with the name of Israelites and Jews? Nay better since Christians cannot be said to be Israelites and Jews, but in a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall analogicall sence; but the <hi>Lords day</hi> may be and is a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:207311:47"/>day in a literall and proper sence.</p>
               <p>And hence it follows.</p>
               <p>First, That it seemes to savour more of peevish perversnesse, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable prejudice, and a spirit of pride and contention, then of Christian humilitie, and love to Gods service, his people, and his truth: that the unaffected use of such names in such sences is many times made a matter of reproach and scorn.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That if any thing could be just amongst men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God and his truth are unjustly dealt with; it were but meet and equall that they who would deny men libertie to call the <hi>Lords day</hi> the Christian Sabbath, should themselves be restrained from cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Preachers of the Gospel Priests, the Supper of the Lord a sacrifice, and the Communion Table an Altar: or at least, that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:207311:47"/>they should not be permitted to restraine the one till they refraine the other: since what they pretend either for or against the one, may as well, or rather better, be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for or against the other.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:207311:48"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX unto the precedent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions, tending to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie some exceptions likely <hi>to be taken to them.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="exception">
               <head>The first Exception.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THen it should seem this Law is not obligatory to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then:</hi> Ergo, <hi>no Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture nor simply morall.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Answer.</head>
               <p>This notwithstanding the fourth <hi>Commandement,</hi> may be simply morall, and a law of nature as well as any of the other nine. Nor is it any contradiction to say, that the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:207311:48"/>worke of the Law was written in the hearts of Heathen men, and yet that the <hi>Jewes</hi> had this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of all other Nations, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them alone were committed the Oracles of God; and that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation of the Law at Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> was intended by God as a further obligation of obedience, unto none but the <hi>Israelites</hi> alone, and those that should enter into speciall covenant with God, as they had done: See <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="exception">
               <head>The second Exception.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your adversary, I suppose, would here deny your</hi> Major, <hi>and say, that that interpretation gives the literall sense and meaning of the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which includeth not onely the common and naturall equitie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, obliging all, but also and more especially the particular determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:207311:49"/>of the day,</hi> viz. <hi>the Jewish Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath: for so Master</hi> Broad <hi>contends. To the</hi> Minor <hi>also he would perhaps say, that your interpretation includes not onely the common and naturall equitie of the Commandement, obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging all, but something else too, which it should not include (as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement respecteth Christians)</hi> viz. <hi>the specification of the time</hi> (i. e.) <hi>that it must be one day in seven: which though he would grant to be agreeable to naturall equitie, yet he would deny it to be necessarily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereby.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Answer.</head>
               <p>Were it not for those two clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses (and nothing else, and enforce no more) I grant the <hi>Major</hi> might be denyed and justly. But that in the literall sense and meaning of the Commandement, there should be included any thing else, but
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:207311:49"/>what the <hi>Grammaticall</hi> constructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the words will enforce, or analogie to other places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the common received principles of Religion require, doth passe my understanding to conceive, nor do I think there is any reason can be given for it. For the <hi>minor</hi> I expected it would be denied, and therefore have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to prove it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="exception">
               <head>The third Exception.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>By this reason is not the second and third Commandment also excluded as superfluous? For the first Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment requiring so and so as you say, doth it not withall</hi> (implicitè <hi>and</hi> consequenter) <hi>require too that we should not worship Images, nor blaspheme his name?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Answer.</head>
               <p>This reason, I confesse, if it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:207311:50"/>any as superfluous, must needs exclude the second and the third as well as others: but to say that the second, third, and fourth <hi>Commandments</hi> are virtually inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the first; the fifth, sixth, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, eight and ninth in the last; and may be reduced unto them, is not to exclude them as superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, unlesse we will say that all <hi>compendiums</hi> and <hi>Epitomes</hi> exclude all larger Tractates and Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries as superfluous. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>He that loveth another, hath fulfilled the Law. Rom.</hi> 13.8. And yet he thinks it not superfluous to say, <hi>Let every soul be subject to the higher powers, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 1. &amp;c. It is true that the first <hi>Commandment</hi> requiring so and so, requires as you say withall <hi>(implicitè &amp; consequenter)</hi> that we should not worship Images, nor blaspheme Gods Name. But will any man pretend it superfluous, that what
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:207311:50"/>hath been once commanded <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitè &amp; consequenter</hi> should again be commanded <hi>explicitè &amp; imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatè?</hi> A great part of Scripture more by the same reason might be pretended superfluous; and that of <hi>Solomon</hi> alone might be sufficient. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Fear God, and keep his Commandments: for this is the whole duty of man.</hi> Besides that it is one thing to imply that a sufficient and convenient time is to be set a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part for solemne worship, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other thing to expresse that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of time which ordinarily is both sufficient and convenient, as the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> hath done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="exception">
               <head>The fourth Exception.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>By this opinion it should seeme that the evidence of a necessarie duty pretended to be</hi> naturalis &amp; perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui juris, <hi>the practise whereof all
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:207311:51"/>men do stand obliged unto, may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon such Mathematicall specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations as few men are acquainted with, it may be none so certainly as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured of, as that they can satisfie the doubts which may be made of them by others: and it seems strange that all men should be bound to do that which but a few, if any at all can cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly perceive a necessitie of, or a truth in those principles whereupon that evidence is pretended to be grounded.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Answer.</head>
               <p>But ignorance argues not an action unnecessarie unto them in whom that ignorance it self is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excusable. They that once did know, and still might have known all that they ought to do, having lost that knowledge through their own default, are no whit the lesse obliged to obedience, although
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:207311:51"/>much more indeed altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to performe it. St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>We are not sufficient of our selves to think any thing as of our selves.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.5. and yet I doubt not but that there are some things which we ought to think, and that as <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalis &amp; perpetui juris,</hi> though naturally (as now wee are) we know them not: otherwise there should be nothing necessary now till a new discovery brought men again to be acquainted with it. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>We know not what we should pray for as we ought. Rom.</hi> 8.26. and yet I presume to pray for what we should, and as we ought, is <hi>naturalis &amp; perpetui juris,</hi> a necessarie dutie which no man can justly pretend himselfe exempted from obedience to. If ignorance were alwayes accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with innocence, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our needed not have said, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:207311:52"/>they do. Luk.</hi> 23.34. Nor would he have said, He that knew not, and did commit things worthy of stripes shall be beaten (though he added) with few stripes. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.48.</p>
               <p>Nor do I in this contradict that which I said in the confirmation of the first Proposition, <hi>viz.</hi> If naturall equitie oblige men of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie to observe a sufficient and convenient time for solemne worship, then naturall equitie must presuppose men able to judge of the time to be so obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, whether it be sufficient and convenient or no, &amp;c. For it suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth that once there was that abilitie in men then when they first entred into that bond, the losse of which abilitie since left them no lesse obliged afterward then they had been before. And I doubt not but that the revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the heavens, and all the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:207311:52"/>of time made by their severall motions were better known to <hi>Adam</hi> in his state of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence; and should have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all his posteritie, had they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued still in that estate by the strength of their naturall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standings, then ever they have been unto any man since by all the improvements that industrie hath been able to make of art and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; and that then both the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie it selfe enjoyned in the fourth <hi>Commandment,</hi> and the evidence of the necessity thereof, as <hi>natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis &amp; perpetui juris,</hi> with all the principles of reason, out of which that evidence might be drawne, were apparent enough and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by him. And if the ignorance and uncertainty of those speculations by which some men endeavour to regain unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and impart unto others the knowledge of naturall things, do
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:207311:53"/>argue the imperfection of that evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which naturall men may now have of their duties in this or any other kind whatsoever; yet ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue they not the things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be any whit the lesse ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther certain or necessarie: Should we therefore deny the fifth <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> which saith, <hi>Honour thy father and thy mother,</hi> to be <hi>natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis &amp; perpetui juris,</hi> and say, that all men are not necessarily obliged to the obedience of it, because few men or none are able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, and certainly resolve upon the truth of those philosophicall speculations which concerne hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane generation, and the varietie of those circumstantiall accidents which make our English proverbe true, He is a wise sonne that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his own father: or those prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of policie wherein the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are between Princes and their Subjects have their first
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:207311:53"/>foundation, and the like: yet it may be the perfect understanding of these would afford no little evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, I say, not unto the equitie alone, but even unto the necessitie of that obedience.</p>
               <p>Again, I do not either onely or mainly relie upon Mathematica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l or Philosophicall speculations to evidence the necessitie of a week<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Sabbath, but principally upon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine discovery. Yet as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> disputing at Athens, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28. alledged a sentence of the heathen Poets to evidence the truth of the Creation, and consequently to overthrow their Idoll-worship: so I doubt not, but that the observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Art and experience may be usefully applyed to convince a gain-sayer of the naturall equitie and necessitie of obedience unto that <hi>Commandment,</hi> wherby Gods people are requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red to set apart one day in every week as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:207311:54"/>time of holy rest, though those observations may be no more either generally known, or commonly received for undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed truths, then that saying of the Poets was. But what the Apostle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith of tongues, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.22. they are for a signe not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that beleeve, but to them that beleeve not: the same would I say, of these testimonies drawn from the observations of Art and experience, they are for an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence not unto them that thinke the division of time into weeks, consisting of seven dayes a piece, to have been made by God himself in the Creation; but unto them that are otherwise minded: to whom they may be as the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines</hi> forges were unto the <hi>Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.20. places to shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their ploughshares, coulters, axes and mattocks in. For how ever it be true that the Apostle
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:207311:54"/>saith, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.3. By faith we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand that the worlds were framed by the Word of God; so that things which are seen were not made of things that did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; and they that entertain the Scriptures as the oracles of God, dare not admit a thought to the contrary: yet was it never held either unlawfull, unfit, or unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie to bring Philosophicall Arguments in as handmaids to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon Divine discoverie in clearing the doctrine of the worlds Creation. And since in this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion of the Sabbath there is now adayes a kind of appealing from the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> to the light of nature, whose eye-sight hath been long ago decayed, me thinks, we may well allow her the use of Art and experience as spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles, or perspective glasses, through which she may see both further and clearer, then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:207311:55"/>of her self she can do, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blesse God that affords us any help that way, then lightly esteeme the lessons we may learn thereby.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="exception">
               <head>The fifth Exception.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>If God discovers his will concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the offering up unto him external and bloody sacrifices of sheep, oxen, &amp;c. upon this discovery man by the light of nature in such manner qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified as you speak of in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this inserted addition) may discern and acknowledge it to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to naturall and religious equitie, to offer up such sacrifices unto him; and yet the thing it selfe,</hi> viz. <hi>this kind of offering or sacrificing is not for all that</hi> naturalis &amp; perpetui juris. <hi>So here might some one say in this case.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Answer.</head>
               <p>If God had discovered his will
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:207311:55"/>concerning the offering up unto him externall and bloody sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of sheep, oxen, &amp;c. at the same time, and in the same manner as he did discover his will concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the setting apart one day of seven for a weekly Sabbath; I should have thought that discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie a strong inducement to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that to be <hi>naturalis &amp; perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui juris,</hi> as well as this. For though as the Bishop of <hi>Ely</hi> speaks, <hi>pa.</hi> 54. these circumstantiall accidents make no alteration of the internall and naturall forme or qualitie of the materiall object of this (or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of any other) <hi>Commandment,</hi> nor conclude by a necessary infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence all those, and onely those precepts that then, and so were ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered to be simply and perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly morall, yet they afford a verie probable Argument to perswade us, that all that which was then and so delivered, was purposely
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:207311:56"/>intended by God to be of the same binding power to the same persons. But to let that passe. When God did discover to his people his will concerning the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up unto him externall and bloodie sacrifices of sheep, oxen, &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.4. &amp;c. he did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all discover to his people that his will was not to require or to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them the performance of that service every where, but expresly confined them unto the place which he should chuse to put his Name there. And the Apostle St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us plainly, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.9, 10. that Gods intent and purpose was not that his people should stand alwayes alike obliged unto those observances, but onely untill the time of Reformation. There is no such limitation for the sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sabbath day, nor did the <hi>Jews</hi> ever understand it so.</p>
               <p>And yet I rest not in this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:207311:56"/>neither, because I know that though the offering up of bloudy sacrifices were limited and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in respect of place, yet other ceremoniall observances were not. Therefore I goe further and say, that God discovering his will in this kinde, upon this discovery man by the light of nature in such manner qualified, as I speake of, might discerne and acknowledge it indeed to be agreeable unto na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and religious equitie, to offer up such sacrifices unto him. But how? not absolutely and sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply agreeable unto naturall and religious equitie, in regard of the thing it selfe required, but onely <hi>secundum quid,</hi> and <hi>ex hypothesi,</hi> in regard that it was required by him whose authoritie is absolute, and his revealed will the rule of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse. For set aside the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and what necessitie or fitnesse can any man by the light
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:207311:57"/>of nature finde in a pigeon or a lambe, more then in an Eagle or a Lyon, to be offered in sacrifice to God? yea what reason why such consecrated things should rather dye then be preserved alive? As types of the all-sufficient perfect sacrifice of Christ, wee may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it fit to be so: but then wee goe beyond the bounds of morall duties, and enter into a considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an higher nature then hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane reason can pretend unto. But in the observation of one day of seven, to be unto the people of God the ordinary time of holy rest, I thinke and I have endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to shew, that nature will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge such a fitnes as is not to be found in any other propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time whatsoever. And this I conceive is a maine difference, that may be and must be observed and acknowledged to be between such things, as when they are dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:207311:57"/>to be agreeable unto the will of God, may withall by the light of humane reasō be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be agreeable unto natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and religious equitie. As for example; dare any man deny it agreeable unto naturall and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous equitie, that God command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, <hi>Abraham</hi> should sacrifice his sonne, and the <hi>Israelites</hi> rob the <hi>Egyptians?</hi> yet neither of them both was <hi>Naturalis &amp; perpetui ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> And on the other side, not to covet that which is another mans, is I suppose without question, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalis &amp; perpetui juris,</hi> and since God hath discovered his will to that purpose, men by that remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning remnant of the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which they have, may dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne and acknowledge it to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable unto naturall &amp; religious equitie, but that which it may be no man ever would have light up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if God had not led them to it
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:207311:58"/>by his Law. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> saith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly, <hi>I had not knowne lust</hi> (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be sinne) <hi>except the Law had said, Thou shalt not covet,</hi> Rom. 7.7. The marriage of one man unto one woman onely, appeares to be <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalis &amp; perpetui juris,</hi> by that of the Prophet <hi>Malachie, Mal.</hi> 2.14. &amp;c. And he proves it by that act of Gods providence in the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he made but one, although he had the residue of the Spirit. Yet who could ever have attained to the knowledge thereof, if God himselfe had not revealed it? So the observation of one day in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as a weekly Sabbath, appears to be <hi>Naturalis &amp; perpetui juris,</hi> by the fourth <hi>Commandement,</hi> and is proved so to be by that act of Gods providence in the creation, that he disposed all time in respect of use, to be employed in labour, or in rest; and for proportion or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily allowed six dayes of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:207311:58"/>unto one of rest: though men peradventure since the fall had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knowne this, if <hi>Moses</hi> had not recorded the history of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So that, it seemes, of things which appeare upon occasion of divine discovery, and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to be agreeable unto naturall and religious equitie, one may be <hi>Naturalis et perpetui juris,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not.</p>
               <p>Againe, peradventure, some would say (which yet I doe not) that externall and bloudy sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were so farre agreeable unto naturall and religious equitie, that they might still be practised by the people of God, so that it were not with opinion of necessitie, and as types in reference unto Christ to come. What else is the meaning of those words in the Bishop of <hi>Ely, pag.</hi> 62. <hi>Our Saviour although he disannulled the old Law in respect of observation in the time of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:207311:59"/>yet he established and confirmed the lawfull use thereof in the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church.</hi> Which words, if wee should stretch them to their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most extent, would I doubt not bring both bloudy sacrifices and almost, if not absolutely, all the rites and ceremonies of the Law within the reach of Christian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and then I presume the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath should be no more excluded then the rest. How ever, I perswade my selfe, the generall practise of the Churches of Christ in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and at all times (which if any thing be, is able to prove a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick tradition) in setting apart one day in every week, as their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary time of holy rest (which is all that I pretend to be simply and perpetually morall; yea, all that is intended in the fourth <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>) and in rejecting the use of bloudy sacrifices, and the like, is a sufficient evidence that they
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:207311:59"/>have alwayes entertained a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent opinion of the one and of the other. So that it is no necessary consequence to say, that because bloudy sacrifices are not <hi>Naturalis &amp; perpetui juris,</hi> therfore a seventh day Sabbath is not, though both be agreeable unto naturall and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious equitie, and that seen one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by occasion of divine discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: since in the one it may be seen, as properly belonging to the thing it selfe, in the other, no otherwise but onely with reference to Gods revealed will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="exception">
               <head>The sixt Exception.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The reason of the Jewes observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it seemes, is to be found appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently in the very body of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, in these words:</hi> For in six dayes the Lord made heaven and earth. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>quoniam, nam, enim: and afterward</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>idcirco.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:207311:60"/>Therefore the Lord blessed the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day - the seventh day? Which seventh day? why that wherein he rested: and that was the Jewish Sabbath. This Master</hi> Broad <hi>stands most upon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Answer.</head>
               <p>The reason of the <hi>Jewes</hi> obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, in part, I confesse, is to be found in the Commandement, <hi>viz.</hi> in that they observed one day in every week, but not in that they observed that day in order, which they did. Neither doe I take that reason which is to be found to be in the body of the Commandement, but added to the explication of it: the body of the Commandement being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised in those words, <hi>Remember the Sabbath day to keepe it holy,</hi> whereof the words following are an explication, <hi>Sixe dayes, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:207311:60"/>And that which followeth, <hi>For in six dayes, &amp;c.</hi> I take to be a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the explication, not of the Commandement it self. It is true, Master <hi>Broad</hi> stands most upon this, that the Commandement designes that day which was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served by the <hi>Jewes:</hi> and so doth the Bishop of <hi>Ely,</hi> affirming it to be the literall and specificall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Commandement. But this which they stand most upon, for ought I can perceive, hath most need to be, but is least of all proved to bee intended in the Commandement.</p>
               <p>The force of the rationall and illative particles, <hi>for</hi> and <hi>therefore,</hi> I acknowledge and confesse, they prove strongly that which they are intended to prove, both the sufficiency and the convenience of a seventh day in proportion, one day in every weeke, to be unto the people of God the ordinary time
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:207311:61"/>of holy rest. For in that God ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served that proportion himselfe, it may very well be taken to be an evidence of his puppose and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that men should observe it too, and use the same division and distinction of time which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe had done, and ordinarily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it so. But to inferre a neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of observing the same day in order, which was at first observed by God, because the same pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of time is to be observed by men that was observed by him, is to dispute <hi>à dicto secundum quid, ad dictum simpliciter,</hi> or <hi>petere prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium,</hi> to take that for granted which may be denyed. That God intended to require of his people the observation of the same pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of time, cannot in reason be denyed: but that he intended to require of them the observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the same order of the time proportioned, cannot I thinke be proved.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="exception">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:207311:61"/>
               <head>The seventh Exception.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I would this resolution were made apparent more fully and clearely. And if it may be so resolved, why doe you make it obligatory onely to Gods people, and not to all men uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally? And doe you thinke that the Israelites did one whole day or other every weeke</hi> vacate solenni cultui divino, <hi>in the time of the grievous Egyptian bondage? or if not, that they did therein violate or goe against a dictate and principle of the Law of nature?</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Wee may put the same case in Christians now adayes under Turkish tyranny and slavery, or the like.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Answer.</head>
               <p>The clearing to the full of this resolution is the thing I labour for: and if it be not as apparent unto
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:207311:62"/>others as it seems to me, I wonder not who know that every man abounds in his owne sence. But since the way of truth is that which I seek, I shall entertain it as a speciall favour from any man that will inform me where I wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from it.</p>
               <p>In what sence I make the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> obligatory onely to the people of God, and not to all men universally, I did intimate before: not in regard of the subject matter of it, but in regard of a further tye put upon them by the speciall promulgation of it at Mount <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai:</hi> a respect which I take to be equally common to the fourth with the rest of the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your instances of the <hi>Israelites</hi> in the time of the Egyptian bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and Christians now adayes under Turkish tyranny and slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, or the like, I acknowledge
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:207311:62"/>to be both of the same nature: and doubt not but that they then might, and these now may, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding their subjection to such grievous slaverie, sanctifie a Sabbath day <hi>vacando cultui divino solenni,</hi> and that for one whole day or other in every week, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not with that publick so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie which <hi>in statu libero,</hi> and <hi>Rep. pacata,</hi> they might have done: yet with such private devotion as God would have been contented to accept from them in that estate, and wherewith they might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage themselves, and cheer up their own souls as <hi>David</hi> did, if not in the same, yet in a case not much unlike: <hi>Psal.</hi> 42. and <hi>Psal.</hi> 43. throughout. But whether they did so or no, since God in his Word hath not thought good to tell us, I think there is no necessitie at all that we should enquire. And both of them and Christians now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:207311:63"/>in the case that you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, I think it more charitie to hope the best, then wisedome to suspect the worst. Which yet if we should suppose and grant, that thereupon it would follow which you seem to fear, that in so doing they did violate or go against a dictate and principle of the Law of Nature; I think it would prove no more then might be pretended, that they did not onely then, but both before and after in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of <hi>Polygamie:</hi> unlesse we will say that to commit adultery was not so much to violate and go against a dictate or principle of the law of nature, as to prophane the Sabbath day in case the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> were simply and perpetually morall: which no man can say, but that withall he must confesse that the fourth <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is simply and perpetually morall as well as the <hi>seventh:</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:207311:63"/>which if it be granted of that one, I hope will not be denyed of the rest.</p>
               <p>Besides that, suppose the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> had been but a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitive law that bound the <hi>Israelites,</hi> and none but them, to observe one day in every week as the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie time of <hi>holy rest,</hi> yet the observation thereof might have been as impossible, at least as dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult and dangerous for them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in the time of the Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonian captivitie (when the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie mocked at their Sabbaths. <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.7. when <hi>Darius</hi> made a Decree that whosoever should ask a Petition of any God, or man, for thirtie dayes, save of the King himself, should be cast into the den of Lyons. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.7. And when we may easily beleeve that others as well as <hi>Jehojachin</hi> and <hi>Zedechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> were bound in chains, and kept in prison a long time together) as
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:207311:64"/>it would have been before in the time of the Egyptian bondage, or can be for Christians now adayes under <hi>Turkish</hi> tyrannie.</p>
               <p>And shall we think that the <hi>Jews</hi> did one whole day or other every week <hi>vacare solenni cultui divino,</hi> in the time of the Babylonian cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie? Or if not, that they did violate and go against a dictate or principle of the law of nature, in disobeying a positive law of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine institution, whereof there is no reason at all to conceive they could be ignorant? If the former, why may we not as well conceive that the <hi>Israelites</hi> did so in the time of the Egyptian bondage? For ought I know, there is as much testimonie in Scripture of the one, as of the other that is of neither any at all. If the latter, this objection will make no more against the simple and perpetuall moralitie of the fourth <hi>Cammand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:207311:64"/>then against the morall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie thereof, if it be taken to be positive: for the divine institution therof, I suppose, wil never be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, nor that to live in disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to a positive law of divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution which men are sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed of that it is such, is to violate and go against a dictate and principle of the Law of Nature.</p>
               <p>The onely pretence that I can probably conjecture may be made to the contrary is this, that the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by God to put a bond of obedience upon the <hi>Israelites</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally as they were men, or as they were entred into speciall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God; but as they were to live in <hi>in statu libero,</hi> and <hi>Rep. pacata:</hi> wherein they might have convenient opportunitie and libertie for the solemne exercise of publick worship. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that though the <hi>Jews</hi> in the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:207311:65"/>time of the Babylonian captivitie, and other such ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>remities should not have practised obedience unto the fourth <hi>Commandment, vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do solenni cultui divino,</hi> one whole day or other every week, yet they should not have lived in disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unto a positive Law of divine institution, whereof they were not ignorant, and so not have violated or gone against a dictate and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the Law of Nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in that case the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> bound them not; and where there is no Law, there is no trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression.</p>
               <p>But to this I answer. First, that there may be solemne actions of religious service privately perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and that all solemne worship is not publick. For to the solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of any action sundrie circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances may concurre, whereof to be publickly performed, is but one, and in defect thereof, either any,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:207311:65"/>or at least some of the rest may serve to make the performance of an action solemne: for I take set and solemne actions to be proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opposed unto sudden and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionall. I thinke the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would hardly be perswaded to confesse that a private Masse were not a part of solemne ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and if she could as easily prove it to be truly religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, as she might that the exercise of it is a solemne action, I see not why she should be blamed for it. Nor can I conceive how solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and privacie should not be taken to concurre in that great mourning, whereof the Prophet <hi>Zacharie</hi> speaks, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.11. &amp;c. when all the families that remain shall mourne, every family apart, and their wives apart. What acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of religious service amongst the <hi>Israelites</hi> was more solemne then the celebration of the Passe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over?
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:207311:66"/>over? Yet one of the ordinances of it was, that it must be eaten in their private houses by every fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily apart; and that none must go out of the doore of his house un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the morning. <hi>Exod</hi> 12.21.22.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if it may be truly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that the fourth <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> as a positive law obliged not the <hi>Jews,</hi> but onely <hi>in statu libero,</hi> and <hi>Rep. pacata,</hi> why may not the like be pretended likewise of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther positive Laws as those which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>estrained their marriage with other Nations, and eating of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean beasts, and the like? Which yet it appears they were obliged to even in the time of the Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian captivitie, and their greatest extremities. Nay if with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists we should thinke that the second <hi>Commandment</hi> were no more simply and perpetually mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, then the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> is pretended to be, but that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:207311:66"/>of the literall and specificall object of it, it was onely positive, and obliged none other but the people of <hi>Israel,</hi> why might we not likewise pretend that it bound not them neither, but <hi>in statu libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> and <hi>Rep. pacata?</hi> And so that <hi>Shadrach, Meshach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> were more precise then needed, when they chose rather to expect a miracle of deliverance in the fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fornace, then they would fall down and worship the golden Image which <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had set up. And the like may be said of other <hi>Commandments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, if we should acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it true, that the fourth <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment</hi> did not oblige the <hi>Jews</hi> but onely in <hi>statu libero,</hi> and <hi>Rep. pacata,</hi> why should this limitation be restrained to it onely upon a pretence that it was but a positive Law, and not as well be extended unto it in case it be simply and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:207311:67"/>perpetually morall? May not the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> still stand in as full force unto Christians, as ever it did unto the <hi>Israelites,</hi> and yet bind them no more then it did these; save onely then when they might have convenient opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and libertie of exercising publick worship? If onely publick worship were required of the <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> on the ordinarie Sabbath, those cases of necessitie wherein they were dispensed with, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wherein the <hi>Commandment</hi> did not oblige them at all, will alter nothing of the nature of it; but that notwithstanding it may be either simply and perpetually, or onely positively morall: for the question now is not whereunto, but when, and whom it binds.</p>
               <p>And so, me thinks, this excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is much like that of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Ely, page</hi> 175. &amp;c. drawn from the necessitie of a morall
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:207311:67"/>possibilitie in all just Laws, which he denyes the Law of the fourth <hi>Commandment</hi> to be capable of in respect of all Nations. For he granteth that the fourth <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> made one day of seven a weekly Sabbath, and that the weekly Sabbath was to be a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall day of twenty foure houres: but he pretends it obligatorie onely to the <hi>Jews,</hi> not unto all Nations; because, saith he, some Nations have no ordinarie weeks containing seven particular dayes, distinguished each from other by the rising and setting, and by the presence and departure of the Sunne: as those that live in the Northerne Climates under 70.75.80.85. and 90. degrees.</p>
               <p>Where first I conceive, there is a mistake of naturall dayes, being divided and distinguished from one another by the rising and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Sunne: which is not
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:207311:68"/>the distinction of naturall dayes (as he understands them, <hi>viz.</hi> dayes consisting of twentie-foure equall houres a piece) but of arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall: the naturall day so under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, being properly distingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by the accesse and recesse of the Sunnes center unto and from the meridionall line, as the artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall day in that sence is distingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by the center of the Sunnes accesse unto and recesse from the Horozontall line: all which are discernable even in those climates which he speaketh of, and so the distinction of dayes and weeks, as possible to the people living there as in other places. The occasion of which mistake, may have been the different application of the termes of that distinction by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers men, some calling that the artificiall day, which others call the naturall and <hi>vice versa:</hi> which not being well observed or not
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:207311:68"/>much regarded, it was easie to slip <hi>a genere in genus,</hi> and to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand that of the one which was spoken of the other by the same name. And yet to confesse the truth, before we admit that defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a naturall day, and that distinction of one naturall day from another, we had need to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish of a naturall day, that it is either that which is exactly such indeed, or that which is vulgarly accounted such. That which is exactly such indeed, may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>dies mundanus,</hi> or <hi>periodus ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quatoris,</hi> being the measure of that motion whereby in the space of twenty-foure equall houres, any one poynt in the <hi>aequator,</hi> or in any other of the paralell circles is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried round, and brought againe to the selfe same meridionall line: and this of all other divisions of time made by the motions of the heavens, is the most simple, and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:207311:69"/>alwayes equall to it selfe. That which is vulgarly accounted such, may be called <hi>dies solaris,</hi> or <hi>perio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus solis diurna,</hi> being the measure of that time, wherein by the diur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall motion of the Universe, the center of the Sunne is carried round, and brought againe unto the same meridionall line: and this of all other divisions of time, made by the motions of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, comes neerest in exact per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection unto that which is made by the diurnall motion of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverse, but in it selfe is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly equall: and of a naturall day in this latter acceptation, must the former passages be understood.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if that pretended im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibilitie were granted, he must likewise pretend it impossible that the <hi>Jewes</hi> should have lived in one of those climates, or else confesse the Law unjust, if the <hi>Jewes</hi> living there should have been bound to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:207311:69"/>the obedience of it: unlesse he will pretend that the fourth <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> did binde the <hi>Jewes</hi> in some places of the world, but not in all: and then it would follow, that the <hi>Jewes</hi> by removing of their habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, might have freed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from that yoke of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, as some esteeme it to have been.</p>
               <p>So in the cases you propose of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage, and of <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish</hi> tyranny, there is no inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience can be pretended to the <hi>Israelites</hi> then, or Christians now, from the bond of the fourth <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,</hi> as of a naturall Law, but so, that the <hi>Jewes</hi> at other times might have been subject to the like, by reason of their obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the same, as to a positive Law of divine institution, if it had been intended onely unto them.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>